<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Tom Philip - Full Stack, Rails, .NET, Android and Boxee Developer]]></title>
  <link href="http://tommysqueak.github.io/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://tommysqueak.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2013-11-23T19:50:53+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://tommysqueak.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Tom Philip]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A test post so we can design the home page]]></title>
    <link href="http://tommysqueak.github.io/a-test-post-so-we-can-design-the-home-page/"/>
    <updated>2013-10-13T17:38:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://tommysqueak.github.io/a-test-post-so-we-can-design-the-home-page</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Chuck ipsum. Chuck Norris built a time machine and went back in time to stop the JFK assassination. As Oswald shot, Chuck Norris met all three bullets with his beard, deflecting them. JFK&rsquo;s head exploded out of sheer amazement.
 Chuck Norris frequently donates blood to the Red Cross. Just never his own.
 Scientists used to believe that diamond was the world’s hardest substance. But then they met Chuck Norris, who gave them a roundhouse kick to the face so hard, and with so much heat and pressure, that the scientists turned into artificial Chuck Norris.
 Chuck Norris never cries, because of this when he&rsquo;s sad he roundhouse kicks himself and it makes him feel better since he knows he is the only one who can survive the roundhouse.</p>

<p> <!--more--></p>

<p> Chuck Norris invented a language that incorporates karate and roundhouse kicks. So next time Chuck Norris is kicking your ass, don’t be offended or hurt, he may be just trying to tell you he likes your hat.
 Chuck Norris once kicked a baby elephant into puberty.
 Chuck Norris got a perfect score on his SAT&rsquo;s, simply by writing Chuck Norris for every answer.
 God offered Chuck Norris the gift to fly, which he swiftly declined for super strength roundhouse ability.
 If you can see Chuck Norris, he can see you. If you can&rsquo;t see Chuck Norris you may be only seconds away from death.
 Chuck Norris&#8217; tears cure cancer. Too bad he has never cried.
 Crop circles are Chuck Norris&#8217; way of telling the world that sometimes corn needs to lie the f*ck down.
 Chuck Norris can touch MC Hammer.
 Chuck Norris doesn’t eat. Rather he kicks ass until he’s full.
 Chuck Norris has already been to Mars; that&rsquo;s why there are no signs of life there.
 Chuck Norris invented a language that incorporates karate and roundhouse kicks. So next time Chuck Norris is kicking your ass, don’t be offended or hurt, he may be just trying to tell you he likes your hat.
 Chuck Norris knows where Carmen Sandiego is.
 The Great Wall of China was originally created to keep Chuck Norris out. It failed misserably.
 If paper beats rock, rock beats scissors, and scissors beats paper, what beats all 3 at the same time? Answer: Chuck Norris.</p>

<p>Chuck Norris is a man of few words. Chuck Norris is not a man of few roundhouse kicks to the face.
 In the original pilot for Star Trek Next Generation, Chuck Norris can be seen powering the USS Enterprise warp drive with his roundhouse kicks.
 When Chuck Norris was denied a Bacon McMuffin at McDonalds because it was 10:35, he roundhouse kicked the store so hard it became a KFC.
 Chuck Norris has already been to Mars; that&rsquo;s why there are no signs of life there.
 When observing a Chuck Norris roundhouse kick in slow motion, one finds that Chuck Norris actually rapes his victim in the ass, smokes a cigarette with Dennis Leary, and then roundhouse kicks them in the face.
 Chuck Norris invented water.
 Chuck Norris once commented, &ldquo;There are few problems in this world that cannot be solved by a swift roundhouse kick to the face. In fact, there are none.&#8221;Chuck Norris once ate an entire ream of rice paper and shat out origami swans and Mister Miyagi from Karate Kid.
 The Four Horsemen of the Apocalypse actually live in Chuck Norris&rsquo;s nutsack.
 Chuck Norris once tried to defeat Garry Kasparov in a game of chess. When Norris lost, he won in life by roundhouse kicking Kasparov in the side of the face.
 Chuck Norris made Ellen Degeneres straight.
 Chuck Norris’ roundhouse kick is so powerful, it can be seen from outer space by the naked eye.
 The Four Horsemen of the Apocalypse actually live in Chuck Norris&rsquo;s nutsack.
 Chuck Norris eats transformer toys in vehicle mode and poos them out transformed into a robot.
 Chuck Norris always has sex on the first date. Always.
 A blind man once stepped on Chuck Norris&#8217; shoe. Chuck replied, &#8220;Don&rsquo;t you know who I am? I&rsquo;m Chuck Norris!&rdquo; The mere mention of his name cured this man blindness. Sadly the first, last, and only thing this man ever saw, was a fatal roundhouse delivered by Chuck Norris.
 Aliens do exist. They&rsquo;re just waiting for Chuck Norris to die before they attack.
 The Great Wall of China was originally created to keep Chuck Norris out. It failed misserably.
 A Handicap parking sign does not signify that this spot is for handicapped people. It is actually in fact a warning, that the spot belongs to Chuck Norris and that you will be handicapped if you park there.
 When you open a can of whoop-ass, Chuck Norris jumps out.
 Chuck Norris invented a language that incorporates karate and roundhouse kicks. So next time Chuck Norris is kicking your ass, don’t be offended or hurt, he may be just trying to tell you he likes your hat.
 Chuck Norris never cries, because of this when he&rsquo;s sad he roundhouse kicks himself and it makes him feel better since he knows he is the only one who can survive the roundhouse.</p>

<p>Chuck Norris can piss into gale force winds.
 Chuck Norris doesnt have AIDS but he gives it to people anyway.
 If Superman and The Flash were to race to the edge of space you know who would win? Chuck Norris.
 Chuck Norris once ate three 72 oz. steaks in one hour. He spent the first 45 minutes having sex with his waitress.
 When Chuck Norris was denied a Bacon McMuffin at McDonalds because it was 10:35, he roundhouse kicked the store so hard it became a KFC.
 Chuck Norris got a perfect score on his SAT&rsquo;s, simply by writing Chuck Norris for every answer.
 Chuck Norris is 1/8th Cherokee. This has nothing to do with ancestry, the man ate a f*cking Indian.
 The chief export of Chuck Norris is pain.
 A meteor, and still owes him a beer.
 China was once bordering the United States, until Chuck Norris roundhouse kicked it all the way through the Earth.
 Chuck Norris once bet NASA he could survive re-entry without a spacesuit. On July 19th, 1999, a naked Chuck Norris re-entered the earth&rsquo;s atmosphere, streaking over 14 states and reaching a temperature of 3000 degrees. An embarrassed NASA publicly claimed it was
 Chuck Norris only masturbates to pictures of Chuck Norris.
 Multiple people have died from Chuck Norris giving them the finger.
 There is no chin behind Chuck Norris&#8217; beard. There is only another fist.
 When Chuck Norris played golf for money, chuck marked down a hole in 0 every time, a pro at the golf club, said to Chuck: &ldquo;excuse me sir, but you cant score zero on a hole&rdquo;. Chuck Norris turned towards the man and said, im Chuck Norris, the man then proceeded to pour gas over his body and set himself on fire because that would be less painful than getting roundhouse kicked by Chuck Norris, Chuck Norris roundhouse kicked him in the face anyways.
 Filming on location for Walker: Texas Ranger, Chuck Norris brought a stillborn baby lamb back to life by giving it a prolonged beard rub. Shortly after the farm animal sprang back to life and a crowd had gathered, Chuck Norris roundhouse kicked the animal, breaking its neck, to remind the crew once more that Chuck giveth, and the good Chuck, he taketh away.
 If you have five dollars and Chuck Norris has five dollars, Chuck Norris has more money than you.
 Playgirl magazine once asked Chuck Norris to appear naked in an issue, Chuck laughed at the opportunity saying “there isn’t enough paper in the world to contain my bearded member”. He then killed the editors simply by unzipping his pants.
 One time while sparring with Wolverine, Chuck Norris accidentally lost his left testicle. You might be familiar with it to this very day by its technical term: Jupiter.
 Chuck Norris got a perfect score on his SAT&rsquo;s, simply by writing Chuck Norris for every answer.
 If you can see Chuck Norris, he can see you. If you can&rsquo;t see Chuck Norris you may be only seconds away from death.
  .Make your own on ChuckIpsum.com</p>

<p>Chuck Norris once tried to wear glasses. The result was him seeing around the world to the point where he was looking at the back of his own head.
 In fine print on the last page of the Guinness Book of World Records it notes that all world records are held by Chuck Norris, and those listed in the book are simply the closest anyone else has ever gotten.
 Pee Wee Herman got arrested for masturbating in public. The same day, Chuck Norris got an award for masturbating in public.
 Chuck Norris doesn&rsquo;t worry about changing his clock twice a year for daylight savings time. The sun rises and sets when Chuck tells it to.
 When his martial arts prowess fails to resolve a situation, Chuck Norris plays dead. When playing dead doesn’t work, he plays zombie.
 Chuck Norris kicked Neo out of Zion , now Neo is &ldquo;The Two&rdquo;
 When Chuck Norris played golf for money, chuck marked down a hole in 0 every time, a pro at the golf club, said to Chuck: &ldquo;excuse me sir, but you cant score zero on a hole&rdquo;. Chuck Norris turned towards the man and said, im Chuck Norris, the man then proceeded to pour gas over his body and set himself on fire because that would be less painful than getting roundhouse kicked by Chuck Norris, Chuck Norris roundhouse kicked him in the face anyways.
 Chuck Norris counted to infinity &ndash; twice.
 In fine print on the last page of the Guinness Book of World Records it notes that all world records are held by Chuck Norris, and those listed in the book are simply the closest anyone else has ever gotten.
 Chuck Norris is 1/8th Cherokee. This has nothing to do with ancestry, the man ate a f<em>cking Indian.
 When you open a can of whoop-ass, Chuck Norris jumps out.
 Chuck Norris isn’t lactose intolerant. He just doesn’t put up with lactose’s sh</em>t.
 When the Boogeyman goes to sleep every night he checks his closet for Chuck Norris.
 Chuck Norris never cries, because of this when he&rsquo;s sad he roundhouse kicks himself and it makes him feel better since he knows he is the only one who can survive the roundhouse.
 Chuck Norris invented a language that incorporates karate and roundhouse kicks. So next time Chuck Norris is kicking your ass, don’t be offended or hurt, he may be just trying to tell you he likes your hat.
 Crop circles are Chuck Norris&#8217; way of telling the world that sometimes corn needs to lie the f*ck down.
 When Chuck Norris was denied a Bacon McMuffin at McDonalds because it was 10:35, he roundhouse kicked the store so hard it became a KFC.
 Chuck Norris doesn’t believe in Germany.</p>

<p>Chuck Norris doesn&rsquo;t worry about changing his clock twice a year for daylight savings time. The sun rises and sets when Chuck tells it to.
 The Great Wall of China was originally created to keep Chuck Norris out. It failed misserably.
 Chuck Norris isn’t lactose intolerant. He just doesn’t put up with lactose’s sh<em>t.
 Chuck Norris drinks napalm to quell his heartburn.
 Pee Wee Herman got arrested for masturbating in public. The same day, Chuck Norris got an award for masturbating in public.
 If you have five dollars and Chuck Norris has five dollars, Chuck Norris has more money than you.
 Chuck Norris won &lsquo;Jumanji&rsquo; without ever saying the word. He simply beat the living sh</em>t out of everything that was thrown at him, and the game forfeited.
 When observing a Chuck Norris roundhouse kick in slow motion, one finds that Chuck Norris actually rapes his victim in the ass, smokes a cigarette with Dennis Leary, and then roundhouse kicks them in the face.
 Chuck Norris sold his soul to the devil for his rugged good looks and unparalleled martial arts ability. Shortly after the transaction was finalized, Chuck roundhouse kicked the devil in the face and took his soul back. The devil, who appreciates irony, couldn&rsquo;t stay mad and admitted he should have seen it coming. They now play poker every second Wednesday of the month.
 Playgirl magazine once asked Chuck Norris to appear naked in an issue, Chuck laughed at the opportunity saying “there isn’t enough paper in the world to contain my bearded member”. He then killed the editors simply by unzipping his pants.
 Chuck Norris kicked Neo out of Zion , now Neo is &ldquo;The Two&rdquo;
 Chuck Norris does not procreate, he breeds
 The Four Horsemen of the Apocalypse actually live in Chuck Norris&rsquo;s nutsack.
 Chuck Norris once tried to wear glasses. The result was him seeing around the world to the point where he was looking at the back of his own head.
 Playgirl magazine once asked Chuck Norris to appear naked in an issue, Chuck laughed at the opportunity saying “there isn’t enough paper in the world to contain my bearded member”. He then killed the editors simply by unzipping his pants.
 Chuck Norris eats transformer toys in vehicle mode and poos them out transformed into a robot.
 Chuck Norris once bet NASA he could survive re-entry without a spacesuit. On July 19th, 1999, a naked Chuck Norris re-entered the earth&rsquo;s atmosphere, streaking over 14 states and reaching a temperature of 3000 degrees. An embarrassed NASA publicly claimed it was
 Chuck Norris has already been to Mars; that&rsquo;s why there are no signs of life there.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Testing Backbone with Jasmine &amp; Sinon]]></title>
    <link href="http://tommysqueak.github.io/testing-backbone-with-jasmine-and-sinon/"/>
    <updated>2011-12-23T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://tommysqueak.github.io/testing-backbone-with-jasmine-and-sinon</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[This is based on an <strong><a href="http://xkcd.com">XKCD</a> leanback web app</strong> I&#8217;m working on that will form part of a html5 <a title="Boxee app developer" href="http://www.greatboxee.com">Boxee app</a>. Think sitting on your couch, remote control in hand flicking through XKCD comics on the TV.

It brings together quite a few technologies and techniques. The end results is something that is separated out nicely (no spaghetti code) that is simple, testable, documented and maintainable.

<!--more-->

<h2>The Specs</h2>
[codesyntax lang=&#8221;javascript&#8221; tab_width=&#8221;1&#8221;]
<pre>describe("Comic Navigator", function(){

  var nav = new Xkcd.ComicNavigator();
  var latestComic = new Xkcd.Comic({id: 101});

  describe("when navigating to the latest xkcd comic", function(){

    beforeEach(function(){
      this.fetchStub = sinon.stub(Xkcd.Comic.prototype, 'fetch').yieldsTo('success', latestComic);

      nav.toLatest();
    });

    afterEach(function(){
      this.fetchStub.restore();
    });

    it("should fetch the latest comic. NB requests without a comic number get the latest comic.", function(){
      expect(this.fetchStub.thisValues[0].get("id")).toBeFalsy();
    });

    it("should navigate to the latest comic", function(){
      expect(nav.get("current")).toBe(latestComic);
    });

    it("should keep track of what the latest comic is", function(){
      expect(nav.get("latest")).toBe(latestComic);
    });
  });
});</pre>
[/codesyntax]

<h3>So what&#8217;s going on?</h3>
<strong><a title="Jasmine BDD Framework for Javascript" href="http://pivotal.github.com/jasmine/">Jasmine</a> is the BDD framework</strong> that is giving us that familiar &#8216;describe/it&#8217; way of defining the behaviour and at the code level the expect-ations. It&#8217;s easy to understand and get started with. It doesn&#8217;t have to be run in the browser as it has no dependency on the DOM, so is CI friendly too.

<strong><a title="Mocking, stubbing, spying framework for Javascript" href="http://sinonjs.org/">Sinon.JS</a> is the mocking framework</strong>. It&#8217;s only being used here to stub out the fetch call, which would otherwise make a call to the server. It  also keeps the call synchronous and gives us a canned answer that we can later observe. It&#8217;s framework independent, so can be used with your favourite Javascript testing framework.
<h2>The Feature</h2>
[codesyntax lang=&#8221;javascript&#8221; tab_width=&#8221;1&#8221;]
<pre>var Xkcd = (function(){

  var ComicNavigator = Backbone.Model.extend({

      toLatest: function(){
        var comic = new Comic()
        var nav = this;
        comic.fetch({
          success: function(model){
            nav.set({"current": model});
            nav.set({"latest": model});
          }
        });
      }
    }
  );

  var Comic = Backbone.Model.extend({
    url: function(){
      return 'http://dynamic.xkcd.com/api-0/jsonp/comic/' + (this.id || "") + '?callback=?'
    },

    initialize: function(){
        this.backbone_fetch = this.fetch;
      this.fetch = function(options)
      {
        options || (options = {});
        options.jsonpCallback = 'comicIncoming';
        return this.backbone_fetch(options);
      }
    }
  });

  return {
    ComicNavigator: ComicNavigator,
    Comic: Comic
  };

})();</pre>
[/codesyntax]
<h3>So what&#8217;s going on?</h3>
First of all, I&#8217;m using the <strong><a href="http://www.addyosmani.com/resources/essentialjsdesignpatterns/book/#revealingmodulepatternjavascript">Revealing Module Pattern</a> to namespace the models</strong> into &#8216;Xkcd&#8217;. The return statement at the end is effectively publicly exposing the ComicNavigator and Comic. Anything I want to keep private I can, I just don&#8217;t expose it. This particular version of the <a href="http://www.addyosmani.com/resources/essentialjsdesignpatterns/book/#modulepatternjavascript">Module Pattern</a> is quite neat as it clearly shows what&#8217;s public and you can use consistent function definitions regardless of whether the function is public or private.

<strong><a title="Backbone" href="http://documentcloud.github.com/backbone/">Backbone.js</a> is a lightweight MVC-like framework</strong> that allows you to structure your code, specifically separating your data from its presentation. I&#8217;m doing it an injustice, it actually does a lot more and is very useful in keeping everything in sync with a RESTful backend, not to mention routing, eventing and validation.

In the above example I have 2 models. The rest of the code uses <a title="Backbone Router" href="http://documentcloud.github.com/backbone/#Router">routes</a> for bookmarking specific comics and possibly navigation to (I&#8217;ve yet to decide on that). There&#8217;s also a <a title="Backbone View" href="http://documentcloud.github.com/backbone/#View">view</a> which will bind to the current comic on the navigator. As the navigator changes the current comic the UI will automatically reflect this. You&#8217;ll be able to see all this in the finished app (coming soon!).

For the Comic model, Backbone has a <a title="Backbone Model fetch method" href="http://documentcloud.github.com/backbone/#Model-fetch">fetch</a> method that will automatically populate the model, given a url. I&#8217;m overriding the url property in order to add a <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/JSONP">jsonp</a> callback (the XKCD service is on a different domain to the app). <strong>Just by adding &#8220;?callback=?&#8221; means backbone will switch to jsonp</strong>. Backbone just defers to jQuery&#8217;s $.ajax (or <a title="Zepto.JS" href="http://zeptojs.com/">Zeptos</a>) method, which automatically detects the  presence of =? and switches from json to jsonp. If there&#8217;s no comic id the service returns the latest comic. I&#8217;m also intercepting the fetch function to specify &#8216;comicIncoming&#8217; as the callback, normally this isn&#8217;t necessary but the XKCD service doesn&#8217;t like jQuerys automatically generated callback.

At this stage, I&#8217;m not certain that the Navigator should be a Backbone model. It makes sense in a typical MVC app and has some characteristics of a Backbone model but then doesn&#8217;t have the persistence/entity behaviours.

I&#8217;m also not happy with the 1st spec, I think it&#8217;s highlighting a smell around newing up a comic. My static mind says inject a factory but that doesn&#8217;t feel right in a dynamic language. Thoughts?

What I&#8217;ve shown is a small slice of the app, to show off some of the techniques and tools. Clearly there&#8217;s more, I just haven&#8217;t written it yet. Once the app is complete, it will show how the other parts come into play, specifically the routes and the view.
<h2>To Recap</h2>
<ul>
  <li><a href="http://www.addyosmani.com/resources/essentialjsdesignpatterns/book/#modulepatternjavascript">Module Pattern</a> for namespacing and keeping things private</li>
  <li><a href="http://pivotal.github.com/jasmine/">Jasmine</a> for BDD style testing ala RSpec</li>
  <li><a href="http://sinonjs.org/">Sinon</a> for test doubles (mocks, stubs etc if you care about the terms which cause more confusion than their worth)</li>
  <li><a href="http://documentcloud.github.com/backbone/">Backbone</a> for separating code into different concerns</li>
  <li><a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/JSONP">Jsonp</a> with Backbone to fetch data from a different domain</li>
</ul>
<strong>Update:</strong> The finished <a title="Introducing XKCD Couch" href="http://tomphilip.me/index.php/introducing-xkcd-couch/">xckd couch app</a>, the <a href="http://www.greatboxee.com/index.php/2012/01/30/xkcd-app-reborn/">html5 boxee app</a> and the <a title="Backbone on the Couch" href="http://tomphilip.me/index.php/backbone-on-the-couch/">backbone on the couch plugin</a> that came out of all of it.

&nbsp;
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[GTD App Review - Producteev]]></title>
    <link href="http://tommysqueak.github.io/gtd-app-review-producteev/"/>
    <updated>2011-11-21T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://tommysqueak.github.io/gtd-app-review-producteev</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<a title="Producteev" href="http://producteev.com">Producteev</a> for Mac is a beautifully designed task list app, that&#8217;s a pure joy to use. You can&#8217;t help but feel that every little piece has been well thought out and designed. It uses contrast and colour to good effect, adding to its looks and helping the user to interact with and visualise tasks.

Adding new tasks is easy. Called up with a hotkey from within any app. It allows extra options (labelling, deadlines, starring etc) to be set too without it being an unwieldy dialog.

Task organisation is easy too, by clicking on the obvious icons to pop-up simple focused dialogs for each property of a task you wish to set (see Setting a Deadline screenshot).

<a title="GTD App Review – Astrid" href="http://tomphilip.me/index.php/gtd-app-review-astrid/">Astrid</a> would be the Android client in this trusted system but if their soon to be released Android app is anywhere as good as its Mac app, then I can&#8217;t wait to see that.

<!--more-->

<h2>How it Scored</h2>
This is how it scored against <a title="My GTD App Criteria" href="http://tomphilip.me/index.php/gtd-app-review-introduction/#criteria">the criteria for a great GTD app</a>.
<table class="gtd-results">
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Criteria</th>
<th>Result</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Quick add</td>
<td>Yes. There&#8217;s an inbox but I think tasks that people asign to you land in here.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Projects/Sub-tasks</td>
<td>Yes, labels</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Contexts/tags</td>
<td>No</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Order tasks</td>
<td>No</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Notes</td>
<td>Yes, multiple notes</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Highlight/star</td>
<td>Yes, importance stars 1-5</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Search</td>
<td>Yes</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Deadline</td>
<td>Yes</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Reminder</td>
<td>Yes</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Recurring tasks</td>
<td>Yes</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Sync with Google Calendar</td>
<td>Yes</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>User Experience</td>
<td>5/5</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>

I put <em>no</em> for contexts/tags but you can assign multiple labels to task, so labels could be used for both projects and contexts. Not as nice as separate but a workaround. Another approach is to use Workspaces as projects and labels as contexts. The problem with this is labels belong to a workspace, so it wouldn&#8217;t be possible to see all tasks for a certain context. Also Google Calendar integration is per workspace, so for each workspace you&#8217;d get a separate calendar and need to connect this to Google.   <strong>I&#8217;d be interested to here from anyone who&#8217;s using/tried either approach and the pros/cons of each.</strong>
<h2>Downsides</h2>
Labels not having the option to span Workspaces.

Having to manually connect each workspace to Google Calendar, thus creating a calendar in Google Calendar per workspace.
<h2>Puzzling</h2>
After 5 labels, you need to expand to see the rest of them (see &#8216;Moving House&#8217; in the Main Screen screenshot). Shame it just doesn&#8217;t show them all or allow you to choose how many to show, there&#8217;s space.

<strong>Update 12/9/2012</strong> - You can actually manually order the lists, by dragging and dropping them into the top half (above the <em>more</em>). So this puzzler goes away.

Dock badges just seem to be for tasks that you&#8217;ve assigned to others or have has assigned to you (I didn&#8217;t get to verify this with someone, so this is I&#8217;m assuming where dock badges come in). I was expecting to get badges for overdue tasks.
<h2>Useful Extras</h2>
<ul>
  <li>Import tasks from Remember the Milk.</li>
  <li>Multiple notes per task.</li>
  <li>Attach a file with each note. Multiple notes mean you can attach multiple files. 100mb file storage limit for free accounts.</li>
  <li>Workspaces for top level partitioning of tasks. Eg Work, Home etc.</li>
  <li>Enhanced for OSX Lion.</li>
  <li>Global hot key to bring up new task box.</li>
  <li>Audit trail. So you can see the history of what&#8217;s happened to a task.</li>
  <li>Assign tasks to other people.</li>
  <li>Collaborate on Workspaces.</li>
  <li>You can create your own filters using quite an extensive criteria and remove the default ones to.</li>
  <li>Smart task entry. Eg ** walk the dog tomorrow, adds a task with 2 stars and a deadline of tomorrow</li>
  <li>All items (labels and Filters) in the left menu can be dragged and dropped to re-order them.</li>
</ul>
<h2>How it Looks</h2>
[gallery link=&#8221;file&#8221; exclude=&#8221;535,536&#8221;]

&nbsp;
<h2>Platforms</h2>
Web, iPhone, Mac and <a href="http://blog.producteev.com/exclusive-sneak-peek-at-producteev-for-window">Windows (coming soon)</a>.
<h2>Support</h2>
They have a good support setup and are listening to customers, with a <a href="http://support.producteev.com/home">support site</a> and <a href="http://producteev2.uservoice.com/">feedback forum</a>.
<h2>Price</h2>
Free for up to 2 users in any Workspace plus 100MB limit. Unlimited Workspaces. Then <a href="https://www.producteev.com/#pricing">tiered pricing</a> for more users, storage and others.

<a href="http://tomphilip.me/index.php/feed/">Subscribe to the feed</a> to follow the rest of the GTD App Review series.
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[GTD App Review - Astrid]]></title>
    <link href="http://tommysqueak.github.io/gtd-app-review-astrid/"/>
    <updated>2011-11-07T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://tommysqueak.github.io/gtd-app-review-astrid</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<a href="http://astrid.com">Astrid</a> is <strong>popular task list app for Android</strong>, that is easy to use and comes with a <strong>host of syncing options</strong>. Incredibly simple and straight forward to use with a pleasant <strong>clean UI</strong>.

It stands out from other task list apps, with some unique features such as backups, random notifications for overdue tasks and encouragements.

Used with Producteev syncing, means I can use the Producteev Mac app as the desktop client for my GTD system. That review is coming soon.

<!--more-->

<h2>How it Scored</h2>
This is how it scored against <a title="My GTD App Criteria" href="http://tomphilip.me/index.php/gtd-app-review-introduction/#criteria">the criteria for a great GTD app</a>.
<table class="gtd-results">
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Criteria</th>
<th>Result</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Quick add</td>
<td>Yes. But it has no inbox</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Projects/Sub-tasks</td>
<td>Yes, lists.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Contexts/tags</td>
<td>No</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Order tasks</td>
<td>No</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Notes</td>
<td>Yes</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Highlight/star</td>
<td>Yes. Importance stars 1-5</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Search</td>
<td>Yes</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Deadline</td>
<td>Yes</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Reminder</td>
<td>Yes</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Recurring tasks</td>
<td>Yes</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Sync with Google Calendar</td>
<td>Kind of. You can add a calendar entry that is connected to the task</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>User Experience</td>
<td>4/5</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>

&nbsp;
<h2>Downsides</h2>
It&#8217;s an impressive app but the lack of GTD specific folders and contexts/tags, means it loses out to those that have them. They of course can be replicated with lists (tasks can belong to more than one list).

You can&#8217;t add a task from the lists home page and you can&#8217;t set the lists page as your <em>home screen</em>.

You can&#8217;t remove or customise the default filters. Like &#8216;Recently Modified&#8217; which doesn&#8217;t feel like a useful filter.
<h2>Puzzling</h2>
Nothing puzzling, just a straight forward task list app.
<h2>Useful Extras</h2>
<ul>
  <li>Time how long it takes to perform a task.</li>
  <li>Workspaces for top level partitioning of tasks. Eg Work, Home etc. When used with Producteev sync.</li>
  <li>Assign tasks to other people and collaborate on lists too.</li>
  <li>Randomly <del>remind</del> nag you of overdue tasks.</li>
  <li>Limited smart task entry. Eg add to list #listname would add the task to <em>listname</em></li>
  <li>Power packs for more widgets, notifications based on location and voice integration.</li>
  <li>Widget for any list/view of tasks.</li>
  <li>Add limited filters.</li>
  <li>Reminders come with encouragements to complete overdue tasks and a host of other reminder settings.</li>
  <li>Specify defaults for tasks.</li>
  <li>Automated backups, should anything go wrong.</li>
  <li>The app is <a href="https://github.com/todoroo/astrid">open source</a>.</li>
  <li>Syncs with <a href="http://www.producteev.com/">Producteev</a>, <a href="http://mail.google.com/tasks">Google Tasks</a> and it&#8217;s own new <a href="http://astrid.com/features">Web app</a>.</li>
</ul>
<h2>How it Looks</h2>
[gallery exclude=&#8221;514,516&#8221; link=&#8221;file&#8221;]
<h2>Platforms</h2>
<a href="https://market.android.com/details?id=com.timsu.astrid">Android</a>, <a href="http://itunes.apple.com/us/app/astrid-todo/id453396855">iPhone</a> (new) and <a href="http://astrid.com">Web</a>.
<h2>Support</h2>
They have a <a href="http://feedback.astrid.com/">feedback forum</a> where employees are active. I&#8217;ve been using the Android app for a long time, as an &#8216;on the go inbox&#8217; and they are always improving the app.
<h2>Price</h2>
Free for all platforms.

<a href="http://tomphilip.me/index.php/feed/">Subscribe to the feed</a> to follow the rest of the GTD App Review series.
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[GTD App Review - Wunderlist]]></title>
    <link href="http://tommysqueak.github.io/gtd-app-review-wunderlist/"/>
    <updated>2011-10-25T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://tommysqueak.github.io/gtd-app-review-wunderlist</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<a href="http://www.wunderlist.com/">Wunderlist</a> is a beautiful looking free app that is unbelievably simple to use. Providing that same experience across all the major platforms and devices. There&#8217;s no need to re-learn or adapt for which platform you&#8217;re on.

It lacks some GTD-esque features but what it does with the features it has, it does very well. It has a lot of potential for a GTD system, should they take note of the <a href="http://wunderlist.uservoice.com/forums/136230-general/filters/top">top most requested features</a>. It also looks like <a href="http://www.wunderkit.com/hAWLdo">Wunderkit</a>, a kind of Wunderlist Pro, is just round the corner which looks like it could be the real GTD deal. Looking forward to seeing that (hint hint).

One little thing I did notice that stood out above all Android apps I use (non task management apps included) is the lack of add button next to where you add a task (No matter what app you use to add something, there&#8217;s an add button next to it). You simply tap &#8216;done&#8217; on the keyboard and the task gets added. It&#8217;s a nice little touch, as your fingers are already on the keyboard.

If you&#8217;ve tried the Android app before and had a terrible time of it, they have released a native Android which is quicker and reliable.

<!--more-->

<h2>How it Scored</h2>
This is how it scored against <a title="My GTD App Criteria" href="http://tomphilip.me/index.php/gtd-app-review-introduction/#criteria">the criteria for a great GTD app</a>.
<table class="gtd-results">
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Criteria</th>
<th>Result</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Quick add</td>
<td>Yes. Into any list incl an Inbox.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Projects/Sub-tasks</td>
<td>Yes. Lists.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Contexts/tags</td>
<td>No</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Order tasks</td>
<td>Yes</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Notes</td>
<td>Yes</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Highlight/star</td>
<td>Yes</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Search</td>
<td>Yes</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Deadline</td>
<td>Yes</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Reminder</td>
<td>No (Yes - on Android)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Recurring tasks</td>
<td>No</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Sync with Google Calendar</td>
<td>No</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>User Experience</td>
<td>5/5</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>

&nbsp;
<h2>Downsides</h2>
It doesn&#8217;t do anything badly, it just lacks some of the features required for a good GTD system. Besides the shortage of features there&#8217;s little wrong with this app. With the features it has, it performs them with beauty and ease.
<h2>Puzzling</h2>
You can set reminders on the Android version but not the Mac or Web versions.

The sync button/notification can often says it&#8217;s  failed (goes red) but then syncs again and all is OK (goes green).
<h2>Useful Extras</h2>
<ul>
  <li>The app is <a href="https://github.com/6wunderkinder/wunderlist">open source</a></li>
  <li>Smart task adding. Eg Include a * to add a starred task. Include the word &#8216;tomorrow&#8217; to add a task due tomorrow.</li>
  <li>Choice of app backgrounds. The wood is my favourite.</li>
  <li>You can share individual lists with people to collaborate on.</li>
  <li>You can share all your lists on <a href="http://getcloudapp.com/">CloudApp</a> and then give anyone the secret url.</li>
  <li>You can show all tasks (or starred ones or completed ones) on one screen grouped by list.</li>
  <li>Overdue tasks appear as a badge on the dock icon</li>
</ul>
<h2>How it Looks</h2>
[gallery exclude=&#8221;465,469&#8221; link=&#8221;file&#8221;]

&nbsp;
<h2>Platforms</h2>
Available on Mac, Android, Windows, iPad, iPhone and Linux.
<h2>Support</h2>
There&#8217;s a comprehensive <a href="http://support.wunderlist.com/">support area</a> and you can <a href="http://wunderlist.uservoice.com/">vote for and request new features</a>.
<h2>Price</h2>
Free for all platforms.

<a href="http://tomphilip.me/index.php/feed/">Subscribe to the feed</a> to follow the rest of the GTD App Review series.
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[GTD App Review - Doit.im]]></title>
    <link href="http://tommysqueak.github.io/gtd-app-review-doit-im/"/>
    <updated>2011-10-13T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://tommysqueak.github.io/gtd-app-review-doit-im</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<a href="http://www.doit.im">Doit.im</a> is a fantastic multi-platform free service, designed specifically for GTD. It has a pleasant simplicity about it, that looks great and makes it easy to use.

Because it is <a href="https://i.doit.im/features">made for GTD</a>, it isn&#8217;t bloated with features and focuses on the key principles of GTD. It has GTD specific lists (Eg someday, next, waiting for etc), filters which make sense (eg contexts, projects etc) and an ever present &#8216;Create Task&#8217; button for collecting those thoughts. All of which help you through the <a href="http://www.lifehack.org/articles/lifehack/gtd-workflow-chart.html">GTD process</a>.

<!--more-->

<h2>How it Scored</h2>
This is how it scored against <a title="My GTD App Criteria" href="http://tomphilip.me/index.php/gtd-app-review-introduction/#criteria">the criteria for a great GTD app</a>.
<table class="gtd-results">
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Criteria</th>
<th>Result</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Quick add</td>
<td>Yes. Into inbox or you can change when adding.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Projects/Sub-tasks</td>
<td>Yes, projects.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Contexts/tags</td>
<td>Yes, both.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Order tasks</td>
<td>No</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Notes</td>
<td>Yes</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Highlight/star</td>
<td>Yes. Starred tasks go into special &#8216;Today&#8217; folder</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Search</td>
<td>Yes</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Deadline</td>
<td>Yes</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Reminder</td>
<td>Yes</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Recurring tasks</td>
<td>Yes</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Sync with Google Calendar</td>
<td>Yes</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>User Experience</td>
<td>4/5</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
&nbsp;
<h2>Downsides</h2>
From the web app, it&#8217;s quite often slow to perform tasks.

The Mini app for Mac, is in need of an update. Key functionality is missing (see puzzling) and missing also are tags, contexts, priorities, recurrences and a project view.

Because of the layout (in web app) I can&#8217;t &#8216;sit&#8217; in the inbox and organise tasks into projects via drag and drop.

Shame it only has task counts for some of its lists (Inbox and Today) and not the others.
<h2>Puzzling</h2>
The mini app is totally unaware of the statues of Tomorrow, Next and Waiting For. Setting a task to any of these doesn&#8217;t sync that change to the mini app therefore showing the task to have the wrong status. Any tasks added with these statuses don&#8217;t even show up in the mini app after a sync, not that there is a way to see a view of these lists anyway.

<h2>Useful Extras</h2>
<ul>
  <li>Projects or special lists can be set as the first screen to open when the app starts up (Android).</li>
  <li>Calendar and list widgets (Android).</li>
  <li>Assign tasks to other people.</li>
  <li>Special lists specific to GTD, such as Next, Scheduled, Waiting for, Someday</li>
  <li>Smart add, so you can add tasks with details. Eg Buy Flour  #Bake a cake ^Someday, would put task into &#8216;Bake a cake&#8217; project and classify as &#8216;someday maybe&#8217;.</li>
  <li>You can create your own filters, based on an extensive criteria and add these to the menu underneath the special lists.</li>
  <li>Global hot key to bring up new task box (Mac Mini).</li>
</ul>
<h2>How it Looks</h2>
[gallery exclude=&#8221;413,451&#8221; link=&#8221;file&#8221;]
<h2>Platforms</h2>
<a href="https://market.android.com/details?id=im.doit.android">Android</a>, <a href="http://itunes.apple.com/us/app/doit.im-mini/id426005879">Mac</a>, <a title="itunes" href="http://itunes.apple.com/us/app/doit.im-hd/id454182500">iPhone/iPad</a>, Windows and Web.
<h2>Support</h2>
There&#8217;s a <a href="http://support.doit.im/home">support forum</a> for features requests and bugs. Although many requests and bug reports seem to go unanswered by the company.
<h2>Price</h2>
Free for all platforms, except the Mac mini app which is only £0.69.

<a href="http://tomphilip.me/index.php/feed/">Subscribe to the feed</a> to follow the rest of the GTD App Review series.
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
